טוב *Tov*, today's דף *daf* is נ"ח *Nun-Chet* 58, and we pick
up at the bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב' *Nun-Zayin Amud Bais*, and
you might remember that the discussion the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* is in
the middle of, which is going to last till the whole end
of today, is the issue of if something is forbidden and it
is growing, a plant or has a certain הלכה halacha *halachic* status,
but let's say forbidden, you have an onion, you have a fruit
that is let's say the fruit is ערלה Orlah *orlah*, let's say
the onion is כלאיים Kilayim, *kilayim*, or another situation which is forbidden
but still have a unique status, like it would be תרומה Terumah,
*terumah* or it would be שמיטה shmita, *shemittah*, and then it's continuing
to grow and the new stuff that grows does not have that
status because
you uprooted the vineyard let's say, so it's no longer growing in
a כלאיים Kilayim *kilayim* type of a context, or it's continuing to
grow in the eighth year, and another types of scenarios in which
the new stuff is not the same as the old stuff. It
was taken as תרומה Terumah, *terumah*, now it's planted, the new stuff
isn't תרומה Terumah *terumah*, it's growing from תרומה Terumah, *terumah* but it's
not תרומה Terumah *terumah*. So the question is: can the new growth
be מבטל *mevatel*, nullify what has the core which is forbidden and
has that הלכה halacha *halachic* status? Would we apply the laws of
ביטול bitul *bitul*? And the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* never spells out what
the reason to say no would be, but there are a couple
of possibilities. One is that because it derives from something of that
status and it grew from it, it's not distinct enough and it's
not permissible enough or, you know, neutral enough in order to nullify,
you know, because I mean the whole thing it said it came
from it and now that it should have the power to go
back and to redefine and to nullify if the whole thing was
just a continued growth of the core, you know, maybe it's always
defined by the core. ר"ן Ran, *Ran* wants to take it one
step further and say that maybe the question is not even really
about ביטול bitul. *bitul* as much as maybe the stuff that grows
really just takes on the status of the original thing. So if
the original thing was תרומה Terumah, *terumah*, the stuff that grows from
it is תרומה Terumah, *terumah*. If the original thing
was ערלה Orlah *orlah*, the stuff that grows from it is ערלה
Orlah *orlah*. So then it's not even really a ביטול bitul? *bitul*
question, it's a question about what's the הלכה halacha *halachic* status of
the stuff that grows. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be
more asking a ביטול bitul, *bitul* question: can it go ahead and
have the power to negate the core? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
has raised a couple of, showed that this is a debate at
least in the אמוראים *Amoraim*, that there was an original statement that
it can negate the core,
that was the position of רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak *Rabbi Yitzhak*, and
then the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* quoted two statements, one of רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* and one of רבי יונתן Rabbi Yonatan *Rabbi
Yonasan*, that said that it can not
negate the core and that it remains forbidden. Okay, so now we're
going to pick up at the bottom of נ"ז עמוד ב' *Nun-Zayin
Amud Bais* where it says the following: אלא מן הדא ela min
hada. *Ela min hada*, the last line of נ"ז עמוד ב' *Nun-Zayin
Amud Bais* from the following, דתניא Detanya, *detanya* we taught in a
ברייתא Braisa, *braita*, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon, אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*, רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon. *Rabbi Shimon* says כל דבר שיש לו מתירין *kol
davar sheyesh lo matirin*, anything that will has a way of becoming
permissible, כגון kegon, *kegon* what's a something that will eventually become permissible
or has a way of becoming permissible? טבל tevel. *Tevel*, grain that
does not have תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u-Maasros *terumos and maasros* taken from
it, that's forbidden, but it will become permissible when you take the
תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'ma'asrot, *terumos and maasros* from it. ומעשר שני *Umaaser
sheni*, how about מעשר maaser שני *maaser sheni*, which has a special
status, not really a forbidden status, but a special status has to
be eaten in ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, but it would be a natural thing
for it to lose its status by itself because you just redeem
it on money, which would be a very common thing people would
do and bring the money up to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*. והקדש *Vehekdesh*, something
sanctified. Now it does not mean according to most ראשונים rishonim *rishonim*
you sanctified an animal for a קרבן *korban* because then why would
it have יש לו yesh lo מתירין *yesh lo matirin*? You're going
to bring it as a קרבן *korban*, end of story. What it
means is you sanctified your car, let's say, for the temple treasury.
So when you sanctify objects to go to the temple for the
temple treasury, the point is not that the temple has use for
your old car, the point is like, you know, when you give
cars for kids or whatever, they don't actually use the car, they
sell it and they use the proceeds. Okay, so when you sanctify
something for the temple, the whole point is that it's going to
have that קדושה Kedusha. *kedusha* removed in the process of them selling
it and then the קדושה *kedusha* will transfer to the money that
the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* sells it for. Okay, so that's something
that is going to lose its status. וחדש *Vechadash*, or the new
grain that grows before פסח Pesach. *Pesach*, which is forbidden, but it
becomes permissible once the עומר *omer* is brought on the second day
of פסח *Pesach*. All of these things right now have a status
of being forbidden, but if, you know, will naturally or will be
very common for them to become permissible. In those cases says רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon *Rabbi Shimon*, לא נתנו בהם חכמים שיעור natnu bahem
chachamim shiur. *lo nasnu bahem chachamim shiur*, the rabbis did not give
a quantity, an amount, meaning that those things are never בטל batel
*batel*, can never be nullified in a mixture. Even the tiniest amount
of this thing will make a mixture forbidden. Why? And the general
explanation is because why should they allow you to basically use the...
principles of ביטול bitul. and eat this mixture based on the fact
that it'll negate what's there? You can just wait till it becomes
permissible and eat it in a completely acceptable way. Why should you
eat something forbidden that's been nullified? Just make it not forbidden. Just
use, just wait till the second day of פסח. Just go ahead
and redeem it. Just go ahead and take תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'ma'asrot
from other grain to change its status of being טבל. tevel. And
therefore, in order that ביטול bittul. is like what you use when
you have no choice. The thing got mixed up, I'd have to
throw the whole thing out. Okay, we can say it's negated. But
here there's another option, and therefore the rabbis did not want you
to use ביטול. bittul, That's normally the logic that's explained. That's the
principle that כל דבר שיש לו מתירים, kol davar sheyesh lo matirin,
something that has a way of becoming permissible, right, אפילו באלף לא
בטל afilu b'elef lo batel is not בטל batel. even one in
a thousand, even the tiniest amount is not בטל. batel. Now here
in the גמרא, Gemara this is said in the name of רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon and as we're about to see, actually the חכמים
Chachamim disagreed with רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon Nevertheless, this does become accepted
as the halakhic principle. As the undisputed—it starts as a debate, but
it very quickly becomes adopted as the halakhic principle that דבר שיש
לו מתירים davar sheyesh lo matirin is not בטל. batel. Let's just
read the response and I'll take your question, Dov. So it says,
וכל דבר שאין לו מתירים, v'chol davar she-ein lo matirin, something that
will not become permissible, כגון, which is most things that are forbidden,
תרומה, Terumah so תרומה, Terumah I mean תרומה Trumah obviously is not
just forbidden but has a special status only eaten by a כהן.
kohen. There's no way something stops becoming
תרומה, Trumah although we will talk about that later today. ותרומת מעשר,
v'trumas maaser, or the tenth of the tenth, right, when the לוי
Levi gets his מעשר Maaser? and he takes another tenth of that
and gives that as a type of a תרומה truma to the
כהן, kohen, so it's a type of a תרומה, וחלה, v'Challah, which
is the separating of dough, when you make enough dough, you separate
a little bit and give it to the כהן, kohen, and also
something that has halakhically a status like תרומה, וערלה, v'Orlah, or something
that grows in the first three years, fruit, right, וכלאי הכרם, v'kilay
hakerem, or something that was a mixed planting with the vineyard, also
the stuff that grows when you have a mixture of seeds becomes
forbidden, and there's no way that any of that has any other
option of becoming permissible. In that case, if it gets mixed up
in a mixture, נתנו בהם חכמים שיעור. The rabbis gave an amount
and they said it will be בטל. batel Okay. Now, how much
do you need to create ביטול? bittul So, by normal things, which
is not what he's talking about because you'll notice most of his
things here are agricultural in this list, but let's say it was
just a piece of חזיר chazir fell in my stew, normally we
would say 60 times as much, right? That's the normal amount. Here,
interestingly in these agricultural categories, and we find that the amount is
a higher amount. By things like תרומה you need one in a
hundred, you need a hundred times to create ביטול, bittul and by
things like ערלה וכלאים Orlah v'Kilayim you need 200 times to create
ביטול. bittul So it's actually interesting here that it's not the standard
60, but nevertheless, after it falls below a certain amount, it will
become nullified. That's his principle that דבר שיש לו מתירים davar sheyesh
lo matirin is not בטל batel, אפילו באלף, afilu b'elef, even in
a thousand or a million parts, right, its tiniest amount is still
a problem, whereas these things will become בטל, batel. 60, 100, 200,
but after a certain point it will become בטל. batel Yes, Dov?
It's just a summary observation. It's so powerful this concept. It means
that something whose identity can actually change through some structure
is
more permanent in a way than something whose identity is לכתחילה lechatchila
more ambiguous in a way. Right? In other words, not ambiguous, but
right, what do you mean by ambiguous? Well, I mean the item
whose identity can actually change through some process is less
susceptible
to amelioration,
it's almost,
so
if you're more flexible you can you can survive more conditions. Interesting,
fascinating. Okay. So, that's רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon, position, and by the
way I should just say just for those that are want to
know the technical halakhic point, all of this is in cases of
מין במינו, min b'mino, when it's the same type of thing that
gets mixed up, grain gets mixed up with grain, your apple that's
ערלה Orlah gets mixed up with other apples. If it gets mixed
up with אינו מינו, eino mino, for example, a little piece of
your apple falls into your
stew or whatever and it somehow gets or gets blended in your
mixmaster with a lot of other stuff that's not apples, in that
case actually it would be בטל batel, one in 60, whether it,
even in the case of דבר שיש לו מתירים. davar sheyesh lo
matirin. But all of this is when it's like and like that
gets mixed up. That's just a little footnote. But anyway, back to
the point. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon lays out his principle that
דבר שאין לו מתירים davar she-ein lo matirin is not בטל, batel,
and let's see—or דבר שיש לו מתירים davar sheyesh lo matirin is
not בטל, batel and let's see what the rabbis' response. אמרו
לו, amru lo, so they, the rabbis, said back to him, והלא
שביעית אין לה מתירים, v'halo Shevi'it ein la matirin, שביעית Shevi'it does
not have ways of becoming— permissible if something has a status of
שמיטה, shmita that status will always remain, right? That has to be
eaten, you have to use it, you have to eat it, you
can't, you know, dispose of it in other ways. If it's after
the time of ביעור bi'ur you have to destroy it. There's no
way, there's no other option than to, you know, use it, you
know, keep its status. And nevertheless, ולא נתנו בה חכמים שיעור velo
natnu bah chachamim shiur and that's also not בטל batel, even in
the smallest amounts. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the משנה mishna in
שביעית: shevi'it: השביעית אוסרת כל שהוא במינה, hashevi'it oseret kol shehu beminah,
שביעית shevi'it fruit that has the status of שביעית, shevi'it, if it
gets mixed up with its own kind again as I said all
of this is talking only in cases of מין במינו, min bemino,
mixed up with its own kind, in that case even the slightest
amount it's not בטל, batel, it remains forbidden, it's, you know, the
whole status applies to the whole mixture. So you see your principle
isn't true. Now by the way, you know, he could say, look
it might, you know, he could say, look maybe I still hold
of my principle that דבר שיש לו מתירים davar sheyesh lo matirin
is not בטל, batel, maybe sometimes there are things that even though
they אין לה מתירים ein lah matirin are not בטל, batel, okay,
you know, but you know there are two parts to his statement.
Number one is דבר שיש לו מתירים davar sheyesh lo matirin is
never בטל, batel. and the other is דבר שאין לו מתירים, davar
she'ein lo matirin, things that don't have any other way of becoming
permissible, is בטל. batel So all they really disproven is half of
his statement, right? That when—that it's בטל batel. when it's אין לו
מתירים. ein lo matirin. Okay, there's stuff like שמיטה shmita that's שביעית
shevi'it that's not בטל. batel. But nevertheless they say it doesn't work
in perfectly to your model. So according to you, שביעית shevi'it fruit
with a שביעית shevi'it status should be בטל. batel So let's see
what he says back to them.
I might say this is a special גזירה gezeirah for שביעית. shevi'it.
Well that's what I said, meaning—meaning all this proves is that there's
some things that are stricter than his distinction, right? It doesn't mean
that his distinction isn't true. You know, first of all there can
always be exceptions, he just has to explain the exceptions. Okay, but
number one is you've only proven an exception to half, thank you,
to half of his statement. You've proven he said that when there
is אין לו מתירים, ein lo matirin, when there's no other option
it is בטל batel. and now you're showing by שמיטה shmita, it's
not בטל. batel Okay, maybe sometimes we're stricter, but that doesn't certainly
doesn't disprove the first half of his statement. Anyway let's see what
his answer is. So now that we've answered his question, the question
for him, let's see what he answers. So he says, אמר להם,
amar lahem, he said back to them: אף אני לא אמרתי אלא
לביעור. af ani lo amarti ela levi'ur. No, even I wouldn't say
the case of שמיטה, shmita you know, would be a—would be not
בטל batel, except regarding the הלכה halacha of ביעור. bi'ur. אבל לאכילה,
aval l'achilah, but when it came to the or the obligation to
destroy it or whatever, we'll see what this means. But when it
comes to eating it, the נותן טעם noten ta'am then it would
be בטל, batel. you would go to the—to the story
of—of when it could—of, you know, once it stops giving off taste,
it's less than one in sixty and it's no longer able to
be tasted then it would be בטל. battel? So what is the
difference here of ביעור bi'ur and אכילה? achilah? What does it mean?
It seems like he's saying that in one of these two things
it's considered to be יש לו מתירים. yesh lo matirin. יש לו
מתירים, yesh lo matirin,
now as I said there's two statuses the fruit has for שמיטה
Shmita or two relevances to its status. One is is that while
it's not yet the time of ביעור bi'ur of destroying, while there's
still fruit food available, you know, this thing is still growing out
in the fields and the animals can still eat it. The הלכה
halacha is is that you have to eat the food, you can't
do other things with it, you can't just let's say dispose of
it. You know, there's a real הלכה halacha, in ארץ ישראל eretz
yisrael if people don't rely on the היתר מכירה, heter mechira, you
know, you have to be very careful that all the food that
you basically buy that has קדושת שביעית kedushat shevi'it you either eat
it or you put it like a—basically you compost it what you
didn't eat and you let it rot, but you don't actually go
ahead and destroy it and throw—and throw it out. Like, you know,
I was once at a wedding and they had wine in Israel
that was not—that was from שביעית shevi'it time and I think it
was—I forget was it they weren't relying on קדושת שביעית kedushat shevi'it
or the people that made this wine didn't participate in the היתר—I
heter mean of היתר Hetter, מכירה, the people that made, you know,
this vineyard didn't participate in the היתר מכירה. Anyway, at the end
of the wedding you had all this leftover wine in all these
bottles. You can't spill it out. You know, that's the הלכה halacha
קדושת שביעית. kedushat shevi'it. The fruit has—it has to be eaten and
you have to either, you know, either like, you know, just wait
till it rots or eventually eat it or—so anyway that's one הלכה
halacha about it. The other הלכה is after this type of fruit
is no longer available out in the fields, the animals—you know, it's
no longer growing and it's no longer there and the animals can't
eat from it, it's considered the time of ביעור bi'ur of destruction
and then actually it's a מצוה mitzvah to destroy it and you
can't eat it. Okay now, neither of those are יש לו מתירים.
yesh lo matirin. Neither of those has any other option than to
follow that הלכה, there's no way around that. So what the ראשונים
Rishonim though say is they say maybe regarding the first status that
you have to eat it during, you know, with קדושת שביעית, kedushat
shevi'it, maybe that's considered to be a type of a דבר שיש
לו מתירים. davar sheyesh lo matirin. What does it mean יש לו
מתירים? yesh lo matirin? What it means is is that there's a
way to eat it, meaning, okay you can't use it for other
things, you can't go ahead and like I said flush it down
the toilet or whatever, but it's not like it's אסור, assur, just
eat it! Okay so it's not—it's in a way when it's at
that stage in a way it's like a
דבר שיש לו מתירים, davar sheyesh lo matirin, okay? Meaning it's not
like it'll—it's
temporary יש
לו—it's not that right, right, exactly. Well that's true, time period. That's
true but— It's also not the יש לו מתירים yesh lo matirin
in the sense that it will lose that status. It's a יש
לו מתירים yesh lo matirin in the sense that you can I
can work with this status, okay? It just doesn't have to be
a problem, I can play within those rules. Okay, so for example,
there's a רי"ף, Rif, it's a complicated רי"ף, Rif, I don't want
to talk about it in detail, but there's a רי"ף Rif that
says that talks about if something is let's say bread is baked
in an oven with meat, do you have to treat the bread
as
פליישיג fleishig or not? And the רי"ף Rif says, well it's like
a דבר שיש לו מתירים. davar sheyesh lo matirin. What do you
mean it's a דבר שיש לו מתירים? davar sheyesh lo matirin? It's
פליישיג, fleishig, it's פליישיג. fleishig. Yeah, so fine, so only eat it
with פליישיג, fleishig, don't eat it with מילכיג. milchig. It's meaning he's
using the concept of דבר שיש לו מתירים davar sheyesh lo matirin
a little bit more flexibly to say if there's an if there's
a way that you can work with it and eat it, then
just work within those parameters. So that's how the ראשונים Rishonim read
what רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon, response here is. Now it doesn't exactly
fit the words of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon. but let's take a
look. So here's what they they read it. So אמר ליה, Amar
Lei,
he says back to them, אף אני לא אמרתי אלא לביעור. Af
Ani Lo Amarti Ella Le'vi'ur. When would I say that the stuff
would not be בטל? battel. When it comes to the issue of
ביעור, bi'ur, of destroying. Now it should be the opposite. It should
be that when it comes to the issue of eating it, then
it's יש לו מתירים, yesh lo matirin, then it's not בטל. battel.
So the logic here is the opposite. So if you take a
look at the ר"ן, Ran okay, three lines, four lines before the
lines get wide, the ר"ן Ran. says the following. אמר ליה אף
הם, Amar Lei Af Heim, it's a different גרסה, girsa, הם לא
החמירו אלא לביעור. Heim Lo Hechmiru Ella Le'vi'ur. So he says, אף
הם לא אמרו שהשביעית אוסרת בכל שהוא במינה אלא לענין
שצריך לאכול התערובת קודם הביעור. Af Heim Lo Amru She'shvi'is Oseres Be'chol
Shehu Be'mina Ella Le'inyan She'tzarich Le'echol Ha'ta'aroves Kodem Ha'bi'ur.
Only regarding the הלכה that you have to eat it before the
time of ביעור bi'ur comes, meaning regarding the הלכה of eating it
is when they said that it's not בטל. battel, וכיון שאפשר לאכלה,
Ve'keivan She'efshar Le'ochla, since you can eat it, there's a way you
can work with it, הוי ליה כדבר שיש לו מתירים. havei lei
ke'davar sheyesh lo matirin. Okay, so although he says for ביעור bi'ur
it's not בטל, battel what he really made this mean is the
exact opposite. What we translate this to mean is when it comes
to the idea of eating it, it's not בטל battel. because then
you could just eat it. Okay, how do we read the next
line of what רבי שמעון says? He says אבל לאכילה בנותן טעם.
Avel Le'achila Be'nosein Ta'am. When it comes to eating it, בנותן טעם.
be'nosein ta'am. What do you mean? Eating it is the stuff that
should be יש לו מתירים, yesh lo matirin, should not be בטל.
battel, So again we're going to have this mean the opposite of
what it sounds to say. So look at the next line in
the
ר"ן. אבל לאכילה כלומר אם נתערבו לאחר הביעור שאם היו אוסרים תערובתן
לא שרי באכילה בין במינה בין שלא במינה בנותן טעם. Avel Le'achila,
kelomar, im nit'arvu le'achar ha'bi'ur, she'im hayu osrin ta'arovtan lo sharei be'achila,
bein be'mina bein she'lo be'mina be'nosein ta'am. Okay, then it would go
by בנותן טעם. be'nosein ta'am. So is everybody thoroughly confused? Okay, basically,
now I see people nodding their heads.
Okay, so
בנותן טעם be'nosein ta'am is a ביטול.
bittul Yeah, בנותן טעם be'nosein ta'am is a ביטול, bittul that's what
he means. Meaning what רבי שמעון, the way the ראשונים Rishonim explain
רבי שמעון. Let me explain to you outside of the text. The
way they explain it along the lines of what I've been saying
is when it's the question before the time of ביעור bi'ur and
the question is that I have to eat the fruit, then in
that case it's like יש לו מתירים. yesh lo matirin. In that
case, that's when they said it's not בטל, battel regarding the קדושת
שביעית kedushas shevi'is and the eating of the fruit before the time
of the ביעור. bi'ur. When that's when because that's a like a
יש לו מתירים. yesh lo matirin. But after the time of ביעור,
bi'ur, when you have to destroy the fruit and you're not allowed
to eat it, in that case I actually would say it is
בטל battel because that case is an אין לו מתירים ein lo
matirin type of a case. Okay, so they challenge his principle. You
said it's never בטל battel when יש לו מתירים, yesh lo matirin,
it's always בטל battel? when אין לו מתירים, ein lo matirin, then
שביעית, shevi'is, why is שביעית shevi'is not בטל? battel It's אין לו
מתירים. ein lo matirin. And his basic answer is it would only
not be בטל battel. during the period of eating it because that's
like a יש לו מתירים. yesh lo matirin. But after the period
of destroying it, when there's no option but to destroy it and
it's forbidden to eat it, in that case actually I would say
it would be בטל.
battel, Right, but in the case in which the יש לו מתירים
yesh lo matirin because you can eat it, so there's no ביטול
bittul because during that time period, before the period of ביעור bi'ur
you're allowed to eat the שביעית. shevi'is. Right, there's no condition under
which that food would become אסור assur to eat?
Right, but it would be אסור assur to do other things with
it. It still has הלכות פירות שביעית. halachos peiros shevi'is.
What,
you can't sell it, you couldn't do סחורה?
schora? Right, exactly, exactly, like תרומה is מותר muttar to eat but
it's only מותר muttar to eat for a כהן, Kohen, you know?
So anyway, but right, it's not that the status is irrelevant, the
status does limit you, but it doesn't limit you in such a
severe way, that's why it's like יש לו
מתירים.
yesh
lo matirin.
So in that case like ביטול bitul doesn't apply? ביטול bittul doesn't
apply.
If ביטול bittul. were if ביטול Bittul? were to apply I could
throw it out in the garbage, I could flush it down the
toilet. Because ביטול doesn't apply I have to treat it with קדושת
שביעית. kedushas shevi'is. Okay, so let's get back. Anyway, so let me
read that again and again I'm just we're not you know I'll
just the words essentially mean the opposite according to the way the
ראשונים Rishonim explain of what they say, but let's just read it.
So אמרו לו, Amru Lo, I'm going to read this again, they
said to him: ולא שביעית אין לו מתירים, Velo Shevi'is Ein Lo
Matirin, שביעית shevi'is doesn't lose its status
and it's not בטל, batel, that doesn't work with your principle, דתנן
de-nan we learned in the משנה: Mishnah: השביעית אוסרת בכל שהוא במינה,
Ha-shevi'is Oseres Kol Shehu Be-mina, that even the smallest amount makes it
forbidden. אמר ליה, Amar Lei, he said back to them. אף אני
לא אמרתי אלא לביעור *af ani lo amarti ela l'bi'ur* I would
only say that that idea that it's not בטל Batul, *battel* by
שביעית Shevi'it, *Shvi'is* regarding ביעור *bi'ur* which means regarding eating it before
ביעור *bi'ur* so when it's a question of eating it that's like
a case of יש לו מתירין *yesh lo matirin* because just eat
it and that's when it's not בטל *battel*. אבל אכילה *aval achilah*
again meaning the opposite here when it's forbidden to eat it and
you have to destroy it in that case it's אין לו מתירין
*ein lo matirin* and בנותן טעם *benosen ta'am*. Okay now what does
any of this have to do with פשט Pshat *pshat*? Okay what
does this have to do with the question about something that grows
and doesn't make the core just a change status of what grows
or not? So it's not very clear at all. The ר"ן *Ran*
says the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is assuming when we're talking about these
things that get mixed together we're not just talking about I have
some of my שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah* a שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah* apple and
gets mixed up with other apples. Okay what we're talking about is
also something continues to grow and that's included in our discussion of
whether there's ביטול *bittul*. So in the case of the שמיטה Shmita
*Shmitah* he says what would be a scenario the reverse of what
we're talking about? Not that the core is איסור issur *issur* and
what grows is היתר *hetter* but let's say it's the reverse. The
core is היתר *hetter* and what grows is איסור issur *issur*. What
would be that case? I've got an onion we'll deal with the
classic onion growing in the ground from before שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah*. And
then comes along שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah* and a little bit more grows
on during שביעית *Shvi'is*. Okay so would that little amount if we
say that שביעית *Shvi'is* is אוסר בכל שהוא *oser b'chol shehu* right?
Or whatever the case would be or whatever let's say it's a
case where it would be בטל *battel* because of you know let's
say it would be one of these other things that you know
would go by a hundred or two hundred or whatever would that
little thing make the mixture forbidden right? Or would it אוסר בכל
שהוא *oser b'chol shehu* or would somehow it not affect the status
of the rest of what was growing? So you've got the reverse
case. The core is permissible a little extra grows. So the ר"ן
*Ran* says the question of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is ah
we've got this case of this onion growing during for six years
during in the sixth year a little extra grows we say now
that it's going to make it forbidden because שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah* is
אוסר בכל שהוא *oser b'chol shehu* so you see that the little
bit that grows can affect the remainder okay can affect what was
there before. But of course that's a bizarre question because we're trying
to ask whether a lot that grows can do ביטול *bittul* to
nullify and make something permissible. It's not really relevant to the question
if if the new stuff is forbidden that it should have the
power of making it forbidden right? Do you understand like one is
can the new stuff that grows which is permissible you know nullify
and make permissible the core which was which was איסור issur *issur*.
That was our core that was our question. We now we're sort
of reversing it and saying the core's permissible a little extra grows
that's forbidden will that make it forbidden? Even if it would that
doesn't prove that something has the power to negate the core right?
Which is what the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* answer is. So גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says ודילמא הא נמי לחומרא שאני *u'dilma ha nami l'chumra shani*
there
we're just being strict
we're saying if a little extra grows during the שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah*
it makes the whole mixture a problem. But that doesn't mean that
when the stuff that the extra that grows is permissible it'll have
the power to negate the core which is forbidden. So you can't
prove anything from that okay. So funny it was so complicated to
get that whole משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* and understand the question and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* just dismisses it with one word well that was
just being מחמיר *machmir*. Yes Rachel.
Yeah I that went a little too fast.
Okay so should I try again?
I just want to get the logic clear.
Yeah I'm going to try again. I'll use some visual aids okay.
Here is we before we were talking about
I want the cases because I don't understand the reverse.
Okay so let me just maybe clarify the cases okay the whatever.
Here I've got my little onion okay and this was a תרומה
*Trumah* onion. And then it continued to grow and now it's like
this big right? Okay so or if this is a I don't
know a
a כלאים *Kilayim* onion and then I uprooted the the vineyard and
then it grew all this big without the vineyard. So the question
is is all this extra growth which is so much larger and
it's more you know it's enough to create ביטול *bittul* but maybe
because it grew from the core can't can't it negate the core
or not? That was our question can the new stuff that's היתר
*hetter* negate the core? We were asking the question we were dealing
with was the reverse. I've got this big onion that grew during
the sixth year okay that's my big onion that grew during the
sixth year and a tiny little extra bit now grew during שביעית
*Shvi'is*. And we're saying oh שמיטה Shmita *Shmitah* makes stuff forbidden even
a little bit this little bit makes the whole thing forbidden. Ah
you see so that the extra stuff that grows has an impact
on what was there before. So the גמרא's Gemara *Gemara's* saying big
deal. It's one thing to say it has an impact to make
it forbidden you have a little bit of forbidden it makes the
thing what's permissible forbidden it's one thing to say we're strict and
that it's able to make what was there originally forbidden. It's a
very different thing to say that the new stuff that grows that's
permissible is powerful enough to negate the core that is forbidden. That
would be being lenient.
Permissible and and being
אסור
*assur*
yeah
they are well they're opposites but but But but what you have
to do, right, in order to make something permissible, you have to
use a principle called ביטול. ביטול basically says there's so much of
what's permissible that the stuff that's forbidden is like it's not there.
That requires like getting over a huge hump, right, to negate the
existence of the thing that's forbidden. Okay, so that's the question, is
it powerful enough to negate the existence? For this little extra that
grew on שמיטה Shmita? to make the rest forbidden, it doesn't have
to say that all of this stuff doesn't exist, that it's negated
the existence of all this stuff. It just has to say that
there's a little bit of איסור issur mixed up and therefore you
can't eat it.
But it's just a bigger ground problem. I mean, I can look
if I reversed it and looked at it the other way, then
it should be the...
No, in one case, for something to be permissible, it has to
have no איסור issur. present. Zero איסור issur. present, okay? For something
to be forbidden, right, it's actually, you're right, it actually is the
reverse. Because for something to be forbidden, it doesn't have to be
all forbidden, even a little bit that's there that's forbidden is a
problem. So that's why it makes a difference. For this to become,
right, for this to become permissible, there has to be zero איסור
issur present. So the mechanism that works here is that this has
to make this into zero. That's the mechanism that works. For it
to be permissible, there has to be zero איסור. Issur So that's
a hard mechanism, to make this into zero. But when this little
bit grows to make it forbidden, it doesn't have to make this
zero, it just has to make there some presence of איסור. So
the mechanism is an easier mechanism.
Okay, so they're not opposite.
איסור and היתר are opposite, but the status of a mixture
doesn't play out. Right, exactly. Exactly, exactly. Okay, exactly.
Alright, moving on. Safety issue?
Yeah, right, exactly, exactly.
The bad stuff can make the whole thing bad, you can stay,
just stay away from it, you can say, but if you want
to make it good you've got to be really...
Imagine, imagine it's poison. That was exactly what I was going to
say. Imagine it's poison. If you, it's not enough that there's only
a little bit of poison, there has to be no poison, right?
So if you, so that's exactly it. To have the power to
totally negate the poison requires a lot of power.
Okay, but this is also because it's מין במינו. min bemino.
Yeah, let's not get to, I know, but let's not go there.
They identify. That's true too. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. אתאן, Atsan, אלא מן הדא. Ella min hada, Let's try it
from this case. פשטה, Pashka, you can learn it out. Now we
turn to the משנה. Mishnah בצלים שירדו עליהם גשמים. Betzalim sheyardu aleihem
geshamim. You have these onions,
and it rained.
And this, there's another משנה Mishnah that's hard to explain, but let's
assume we're talking about, it's the sixth year, they're growing in the
sixth year, and now it began to be the שמיטה Shmita year,
and it rained.
And they continued to grow during the שמיטה Shmita year, or that's
the question. Did they grow fundamentally, basically, was all their growth in
the sixth year or did they continue to grow in the שמיטה
Shmita year? וצמחו, Vetzamchu, and they sprouted forth, which let's say there's
a debate in the ראשונים Rishonim how to read this, but let's
say it means that they, that you know, that some of their
leaves, you know, grew out of the ground. You don't know how
much grew under the ground or maybe some of the onion grew,
but the question is did it grow from the שמיטה Shmita ground
of שמיטה Shmita. or did it just grow from the rain? Because
it mostly had grown in the sixth year. אם היו עלים שלהם
שחורים, Im hayu alim shelahem shchorim, if the leaves were like black
or you know, some type of a black-like color, אסורים, assurim, then
it's forbidden. Somehow, don't, please don't ask me, I don't understand this.
Somehow that's an indication that its fundamental growth had been in the
sixth year and therefore any additional growth was just sort of the
onion growing naturally, but not by virtue of it having been, you
know, sort of getting the nutrients from the ground, that's the assumption.
Okay, so then it means it's permissible?
Did I say permissible? I'm sorry, I'm sorry, אסורים, assurim, excuse me,
I misread it, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I don't know,
okay, my, I jumped ahead, I misread that. Okay, let's do that
again. אם היו עלים שלהם שחורים, Im hayu alim shelahem shchorim, if
the leaves were black, אסורים, assurim, it's forbidden, thank you. It means
that we assume some of it did grow on the שמיטה Shmita?
year. Yeah, I flipped the case, I'm sorry. Some of it did
grow on the שמיטה Shmita year and therefore it's forbidden. הוריקו, Horiku,
if however they are a bright green or something or they turned
green, מותרים, Mutarim, then it's permissible, then somehow we assume that it
all grew on the sixth year. Okay, or that any additional growth
the way the ראשונים Rishonim say, maybe it grew from the rain
but it didn't continue to grow from the nutrients of the ground.
Again, exactly when did it turn black, when did it turn green?
How is it that something doesn't grow from the ground? It's, I
don't know the answer to any of this. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר, Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos omer, Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos says, אם
יכולים להיתרש בעלים שלהם, im yecholim lehitaresh ba'alim shelahem, if the leaves
are so well connected or the leaves are so strong that you
can pull it up by its leaves, אסורים, assurim, then it's forbidden
because then that somehow shows that it continued to grow during the
שמיטה Shmita year. Don't ask me how. Okay, anyway, וכנגדן למוצאי שביעית
מותרים. uchenegdam l'motzai Shvi'it mutarim. And opposite is and the same would
be in the reverse going from the seventh year to the eighth
year, right? Because in the seventh year to the eighth year if
it grew during the same situation which would be permissible from six
to seven would be forbidden from seven to eight, because if it's
permissible from six to seven it means you say it grew in
the six. So if that scenario from seven to eight would be
forbidden because then it's growing in the seven and the same in
the reverse. Okay. למימרא, Lemeimra, anyway says the Gemara, what you see
from this is without worrying exactly about the color of the leaves
and how that makes sense, דגידולי היתר מעלין את האיסור. Degidulei heter
ma'alin et ha'isur. Now, the Gemara wants to say one minute, why
when the seventh goes into the eighth, right, if it's so there'd
be case where it'd be permissible when we say it's grew, when
we say the color of the leaves indicate that it continued to
grow, so why would it continue to grow in the eighth year,
does it make it permissible? We're back to the same question. So
what if there's some additional growth in the eighth year? What about
the core that was שמיטה? Shmita. Right, everybody get it? If it's
a scenario where we say it continued to grow in the come
following year, then we would say that some seven going to eight
is permissible, why is that? Don't you see that the additional amount
negates the core? And here we're actually being lenient, we're saying it
negates the core. So the Gemara says ודילמא במדוכנים. Vedilma bimduchanim. So
now the Gemara introduces a new thing, maybe the case would be
that you ground it up. And somehow if you ground it up,
that would change the status. Not exactly clear why, but what you
see from the Gemara is that the reason that we say that
the core can't negate, that the additional can't negate the core could
be my god, the whole thing the whole onion was there before,
right? Logic of negating is you say that the problem doesn't exist
anymore. The whole onion was there before it's just a bigger onion.
And now you're going to tell me that the same onion that
before was forbidden is now permissible because it's a bigger onion? But
it was the whole it was that onion was what was started
with. Okay, so that seems to be some of the logic that
you can't say it negates since the whole thing is just a
growing of the original thing that's forbidden. But if you actually grind
it up and you turned it into,
you know, onion juice or something or minced onion, onion powder, it's
not the same thing. And then we would just go by the
quantities and we wouldn't have the concept that it's still the same
thing and how could you say that it's permissible. Okay, one minute.
Okay. אלא מן הדא, let's try another thing. דתניא, detanya, we taught
in a Baraita.
Good thing that the size of the daf reflects their difficulty. המנכש
עם הכותי בחסיות. Hamnakeish im hakuti bechasyot.
Somebody is weeding with a Samaritan who's not keeping the laws of
תרומות ומעשרות, Trumot u'ma'asrot at least not in the same way, and
with these things which are called like these leafy plants or as
we'll see, they're the exact type things we're talking about like the
onions and so on. Now, אוכל מהן אכילת עראי, Ochel mehen achilat
arai, so we have to assume that now here you are you're
weeding the plants with him, and as we know, workers right are
allowed to under some conditions eat from the, you know nibble on
the food that they're working with, if they're working in the field.
So you assume that the stuff that he planted
was stuff
that didn't have תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'ma'asrot taken from him, I mean
what were the seeds, what were the original stuff that he planted?
Okay, but nevertheless even if it didn't have תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'ma'asrot.
taken from it, the law is that as it's growing and before
it's been processed, you can still go ahead and eat, you know
just like a snacking, that's what אכילת עראי Achilat arai is. ומעשרן
ודאי. Uma'asran vadai.
And if he gives you some of that vegetables or fruit, you
know in as your fee, then you it's not דמאי, Demai, דמאי
Demai means maybe תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'ma'asrot were taken from it, no,
they definitely were not and therefore you're fully obligated to take תרומות
ומעשרות. trumos umaasros Okay, that's not relevant to us, that's just whether
we assume the status of the food that you're working with has
been taken תרומות ומעשרות trumos umaasros. or not and it says we
assume it has not.
רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer, now this
is what's relevant to us. רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar says,
אם ישראל חשוד על השביעית, Im Yisrael chashud al hashevi'it, if you're
working with a parallel case, not the same case, a Jew not
a Samaritan, who is suspect of keeping the laws of שביעית, meaning
it's very possible that here you are it's the eighth year, but
it's possible that he the stuff that's growing now is stuff that
he planted and harvested in the seventh year and he didn't keep
the laws of the שמיטה Shmita, and it's possible that the stuff
is growing again this gets to our case growing from שמיטה Shmita,
fruit. Right, you got it? You're now working with him in his
onion field or his wheat field or whatever it is, but maybe
the seeds that he used were from שמיטה Shmita stuff because he's
not careful about how he deals with שמיטה Shmita stuff.
Okay. למוצאי שביעית מותר. Lemotzei shevi'it mutar. But now it's the eighth
year, it's okay, you can go ahead and nibble on the food
and eat the food and whatever and you don't have to be
concerned that it has the status of שמיטה. Shmita Now why do
I not have to be concerned that it has the status of
שמיטה? Shmita If he's חשוד על השביעית, Chashud al hashevi'it, he's suspect,
then maybe this onion field that I'm working in came from שמיטה
Shmita, onions. So doesn't this show that even if it came from
שמיטה Shmita onions the continued growth negates the core. That seems to
be the question. So the גמרא Gemara says למימרא, leimra, this shows
you דגידולי היתר, digidulei hetter, the stuff that grows from what is...
that grew, that now the new stuff is permissible, מעלין את האיסור,
malin es ha'issur, they negate the core, the original amount, the
core, and they make it all permissible, because here you are, you're
nibbling on these onions that grew in the eighth year, but that
might have had a... that might have come from a core that
was שמיטה. Shmita So you see that the principle of ביטול works.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, maybe ודלמא בדבר שזרעו כלה, vedilma
bedavar shezaro kalah, because I've been saying onions because I've been anticipating
the end of the גמרא. Gemara. But the גמרא Gemara. said, how
do you know what type of field we're talking about? Maybe it's
not an onion field, maybe it's a wheat field. What would be
the difference? Well, you tell me, what's the difference based on the
question we're asking between whether you're dealing with onions or wheat?
Well, yes, but, but the difference is, well, yes, but it still
would have the קדושה. The difference would be that the onion, you
have the core, and it just continues to grow. You have the
same thing that was forbidden plus the additional growth. Right, the... wheat,
you take the seeds and you plant them, the new wheat stalk
that grows and all those kernels up there, it came from that
original kernel, but you don't have the original kernel here anymore. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says our whole question was when you have
the original core and you have growth, should the growth negate the
core? That would only be something like an onion, something כעין זרעו
כלה, k'ein zaro kalah, the seed does not disintegrate. You have the
original core. But something שזרעו כלה, shezaro kalah, the seed disintegrates, and
what you have is all new stuff, that would not be a
problem.
That could be true of any fruit or...
That would be true, right, exactly. That's just called גידולין, gidulin, that's
just stuff that grew from an original seed, but it does not
have the core present.
As opposed to ירק. yerek.
Exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says ודלמא בדבר שזרעו כלה, vedilma bedavar
shezaro kalah, ודלמא בדבר שזרעו כלה, vedilma bedavar shezaro kalah, maybe we're
dealing with something like wheat or something where the original seed has
disintegrated and that's why it's permissible. גמרא Gemara says התניא, ha tanya,
no, because it says that you're dealing with חסיות, chasayos, and what
are חסיות? chasayos? I think it comes probably from the word חסא,
chasa, which is like lettuce or vegetables. So let's see, we taught
in a ברייתא, Braisa, אלו הן חסיות, elu hein chasayos, the following
are considered חסיות, chasayos, that was the description that the משנה said,
that was what you were working with was
חסיות, chasayos, and here's what חסיות chasayos are. כגון הלוף והשום והבצלים.
kegon haluf hashum vehabetzalim.
So לוף luf which I forget, what's לוף? luf? Does anybody have
an English?
It's a member of the onion family.
What? It's a type of onion?
Leek I thought it was לופא, lufa, I thought it was
a leek. Others maintain it doesn't even use seeds.
Alright, so either way, some type of a vegetable that's like that,
right, or garlic or onions where basically they continue to grow and
we're not talking about you plant it and something new grows from
it, but something that just continues to grow. So it is exactly
the case we talked about, and it sounds like the new growth
negates the core. So doesn't this prove our case? So the גמרא
Gemara says ודלמא במדוכנין. vedilma bemiduchanim. No, like we said before, we've
got a new answer. Maybe we're talking that the stuff isn't in
its original state. We're talking that the stuff has been ground up,
and if it's been ground up, maybe that's what allows for the
ביטול. So the גמרא Gemara. says חשוד על השביעית קתני, chashud al
hashevi'is katani, but it says that the guy is suspect for שמיטה,
Shmita, so therefore we're not talking that it's ground up. Why? What's
the logic? Just because he's suspect for שמיטה, Shmita? how do we
know it's not ground up? So the ראשונים say, well, you know,
if we were to say that the scenario is one, to read
that into the ברייתא, Braita, that the scenario is one that it's
ground up, would only make sense if the person were sensitive to
the הלכות halachos and was trying to find a way to deal
with the problem, then maybe he would have ground it up, although
you're not supposed to, that's sort of like אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה.
ein mevatlin issur l'chatchila. But the only reason to assume that was
the scenario was by somebody who knew and was concerned about the
issues. But if you don't know about the issues, how can we
read that into this case that it's ground up? There you are,
you're working in the field, you're eating from the vegetables. How can
we read in the scenario that it's ground up? So the גמרא
Gemara,
says ודלמא בתערובת. vedilma beta'aroves. Okay, well maybe though again, it doesn't
mean that you're eating straight from the vegetables in the field, maybe
it's a scenario where those vegetables got mixed up with other vegetables,
and that's why it's בטל, but not that you're eating straight from
the vegetables in the field and the stuff that had a core
and that grew. So the גמרא Gemara says no המנכש קתני, hamenakesh
katani,
it says that you're weeding the field, which means you're eating straight
from the vegetables that are growing in the field. So here we
have a case where it doesn't seem like you can get around
from it. You're eating straight from the vegetables that are growing in
the field that began grow... that the core was from שמיטה Shmita
but continued to grow afterwards, and it sounds like it's allowed. So
this seems to be a great case where we say that the
stuff that grew negates the core. So this seems to prove our
case. So the גמרא Gemara says... גמרא Gemara's says לימא תהוי תיובתא
דרבי יוחנן ורבי יהונתן, Lema tavei tivta d'Rabbi Yochanan v'Rabbi Yehonasan, let's
say we finally now can show a clear contradiction to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהונתן Rabbi Yehonasan and show that the stuff
that grows does negate the core. So אמר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi
Yitzchak, רבי יצחק says שאני שביעית הואיל ואיסורה על ידי קרקע ביטולה
נמי על ידי קרקע. Shanya shevi'is ho'il v'issurah al yedei karka bitulah
nami al yedei karka. Fascinating new answer here, new concept to bring
to this whole discussion. Maybe the idea that the growth negates the
core is only true by שמיטה Shmita, because שמיטה Shmita focuses on
the land. And since שמיטה Shmita focuses on the land, you have
to let the land rest,
therefore, continued growth while it's planted and in the land can be
meaningful and can negate what was there before. What does this mean?
Who cares that because it's in the land, what does that have
to do with the laws of ביטול? So I will tell you
what I think it means and then I'll tell you an interesting
different approach that תוספות Tosafos has. What I think it means is
by שמיטה, Shmita right, the real question is in a way the
question we ask ourselves when we're dealing with an onion. If I
told you here's an onion, last year was a שמיטה Shmita, year,
this year wasn't a שמיטה Shmita year. Here's an onion, right, is
the question you would ask yourself when you wanted to say what's
its status, would you say to yourself like how much of it
grew during שמיטה, Shmita how much of it grew after שמיטה? Shmita,
No, you'd more want to just assign a label to it and
say like which year is this from, right? Like, and so therefore
the focus is not so much, if I let's contrast that to
a case of an apple from an ערלה Orlah tree. The apple
from the ערלה Orlah tree, the stuff you know the focus is
like the apple is forbidden, right? You focus on like the object
directly. Here it seems to be, this is the way I'm reading
it, that you focus more on like, you know, did it come
from the, you know, from the land last year? Did it come
from, you know, the land this year? And therefore maybe you can
make like a sort of, you know, a statement about it in
its totality. So even if it started growing in the seventh year,
if you basically continued to grow in the eighth year and you
sort of, you know, remove, you know, you pulled it out of
the ground in the eighth year, you know, and if the majority
of it grew in the eighth year, you can say it's an
eighth-year fruit, it's not a seventh-year fruit. The majority of it grew,
you don't focus on, what do you mean? Well, this part of
it was the seventh-year fruit and this part of it was an
eighth-year fruit, and does the, you know, X amount, you know, twenty
grams negate the ten grams? You don't necessarily look at it in
terms of the quantity, you say which
year is this from? So if the majority grew in the eighth
year, it's from the eighth year, and that defines its entire status.
Whereas other types of things like if this thing was תרומה and
it continued to grow, you don't say which year it was from,
you say you started with a core that was תרומה and then
more stuff grew out of it. You started with a core that
was ערלה Orlah, and then more stuff continued to grow. So because
the question you're asking here is which year is this from, that
you might be able to define based on the majority and that's
how come in that case it works where it wouldn't necessarily work
in another case. Okay, that's how I would like to understand the
answer of the גמרא. Yes, it works here because here we're not
saying X grams, you know, of איסור of שמיטה Shmita plus X
grams of eighth year and which one is bigger and which one
negates, we're asking a question of just which year is it from?
Okay, and that allows us to go by the majority as opposed
to other areas. תוספות Tosafos says a different answer. תוספות Tosafos says
what it means is one happens by itself as opposed to something
that you are like actively doing. What does that mean? If you
think about the scenarios of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and רבי יהונתן,
Rabbi Yehonasan, if you remember back to yesterday, one of them was
that you grafted a branch from a, you know, an ערלה Orlah
tree to a non-ערלה tree. And the other one was that you
uprooted a vineyard in which an onion was growing. So תוספות Tosafos
points out that is in both of those cases you did something,
you actively did something to create the היתר, right? You had ערלה,
you had כלאיים, Kilayim. and then you went and you made it
non-ערלה by grafting the branch, or you made it non-כלאיים by uprooting
the vineyard. So תוספות Tosafos says, well, that's sort of like an
אין מבטלין איסור לכתחילה. Ein mevatlin issur l'chatachila. We can't like let
you, you know, give you credit if you went ahead and you
actively did something to make it permissible. That's sort of like trying
to get around the law. Okay, now of course not trying to
get around the law, I'm simply trying to improve the situation, you
know, by removing the כלאיים. But that's what תוספות Tosafos wants to
read. That's not פשט Pshat in the גמרא. פשט Pshat in the
גמרא focuses on what's distinctive about שמיטה, Shmita the focus on the
land. But תוספות Tosafos wants to say, well, really what it means
is in the שמיטה Shmita case it just grew naturally, you didn't
do anything to make it permissible, so therefore in that case we'll
give you a pass. But if you actively worked to make it
permissible, maybe that's a little counterintuitive, but that's sort of like מבטלין
איסור לכתחילה, Mevatlin issur l'chatachila, we're not going to give you a
pass. So I don't think it's פשט Pshat in the גמרא but
I did want to mention it. Okay, I've been putting some questions
on poll so if you had a few questions.
No, no, no, it's just you've answered.
Okay, fine. All right. So now the גמרא finally seems to.
By שמיטה Shmita
we have good evidence that the stuff that grows in the eighth
year negates what grew in the seventh. Does this prove that what
continues to grow negates the core? Rejects רבי יוחנן רבי יונתן and
the גמרא says maybe שמיטה Shmita is a unique category because of
the focus on the land, and like I said there maybe we
want to just ask one big question, which year did it grow
from, and not to subdivide the fruit itself. Okay, so even though
we are lenient by שמיטה, Shmita it doesn't necessarily mean that we
would say the same by other things. So now let's continue in
the גמרא.
One minute says the גמרא,
הרי מעשר, harei maaser, how about מעשר? Maaser דאיסורא על ידי קרקע,
de'issura al yedei karka, that is defined by the land it grows
from, ואין ביטולו על ידי קרקע, ve'ein bitulo al yedei karka, but
the additional growth does not negate. Okay, so here we're going actually
after going through this whole proving that by שמיטה the additional growth
does negate, we're going to show that by מעשר Maaser the additional
growth does not negate. Why not? דתניא, we taught a ברייתא, Braita
ליטרא מעשר טבל, litra maaser tevel, you have מעשר Maaser of טבל.
tevel? How do you have מעשר Maaser of טבל? tevel So what
it means is you gave your מעשר Maaser to the לוי, Levi,
and the לוי Levi has to take תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, a
tenth of a tenth to give to the כהן. Kohen. If he
does not take תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, then the מעשר Maaser, still
has a טבל tevel. status, it's forbidden to be eaten, it's just
like any other טבל. tevel, Okay, so therefore you have this מעשר,
Maaser didn't have to be talking about this scenario but this is
the scenario. The לוי Levi takes his מעשר Maaser that he does
not have, that is still טבל, tevel, and what does he do
with it?
שזרעה בקרקע, shezra'ah bekarka, and he went ahead and before taking his
תרומת מעשר, trumas maaser, he planted this grain, he planted this grain
or let's say these onions, we don't know exactly what it is,
seeds, onions, whatever it is, he planted it, והשביחה, vehishpicha, and then
it continued to grow, והרי היא עשר ליטרין, vaharei hi esser litrin,
and now it's ten times the amount, it's ten liters worth. Okay,
in this case, חייבת במעשר ובשביעית, chayaves bemaaser uvishviis,
you have to, the new stuff is טבל, it's just new stuff
that grows, so what's the law of the new stuff that grows?
You take מעשר Maaser from it. If the new year is a
שמיטה year, then it has the status of שמיטה, it's just like
it grew this year.
ואותה ליטרא, ve'osah litra, here's really the question, but what about in
this new stuff that grew, there's an original one unit, now I
have ten units, but there's the one unit's worth originally that didn't
have תרומה and that didn't have תרומת מעשר trumas maaser taken from
it. What do I do about that original single unit? So that
single unit, מעשר עליה ממקום אחר לפי חשבון, maaser aleha mimakom acher
lefi cheshbon,
so you take מעשר Maaser from another place, meaning I say I've
got this now ten, now that's why we should assume that we're
talking about something not the seeds, because then I wouldn't have the
original thing there, and this makes it sound like the original thing
is there. So I took this one liter of onions, I planted
it, now I've got ten liters worth of onions because it all
grew and became much bigger onions, they were just tiny little bulbs
to start with. Okay, so what do I do about taking the
תרומת מעשר trumas maaser from that original one liter? So I go
have to go to some other onions and separate out and say
I've got one liter there, I've got one liter here of מעשר
Maaser onions that are very distinct, I haven't planted or whatever, I
know exactly what they are, so I'm going now take out of
this, I have ten, I have one liter here and one liter
there, I'm going to take point two liters, point one for this,
plus a point one for the stuff that's mixed up there, because
I can't take the stuff that's mixed up there, I don't know
which is which, it's all mixed together, right, it's all just additional
growth. So I'll take here point two, the point one for this
one liter plus a point one that goes on the other one
liter mixed up, and that'll be my תרומת מעשר. trumas maaser. That's
what the ברייתא is saying. But what do you see? What's relevant
for us is that the original unit has not been negated. I
still have to worry about that original unit. Okay, so we just
got through proving that by שמיטה the original amount is negated, here
we're showing that by מעשר Maaser the original amount is not negated.
How do you reconcile this, and can this fit into your whole
concept that when it comes with the focus is on the land,
that makes a difference? So let's take a look at the גמרא's
answer. אמרי, amri, you can say, you should say, מעשר דיגון הוא
דקגרים לה, maaser digun hu dekagrim lah, by מעשר Maaser also, it's
not really about the land that the focus is, it's about the
דיגון, digun, which is basically the putting it into the pile and
the smoothing it over, they learn that something is not obligated, grain
is not obligated in תרומות Trumos ומעשרות until after it's like threshed
and winnowed and made into a pile and the pile is smoothed
over, and only at that stage is it fully obligated in תרומות
ומעשרות. So what the גמרא says here is actually, this works beautifully
in our structure, we were saying that the only time the additional
growth sort of matters and can be lenient is by שמיטה because
שמיטה focuses on the land. You say well מעשר Maaser also focus
on the land? That's not true, מעשר Maaser. focuses on the grain.
Yes, the grain grew. from the land, but ultimately, it's not a
question of which year did this grow from and which land did
this grow from, the question is once the grain is processed, then
it's obligated in מעשר.
Maaser מעשר אדם Maaser Adam focuses essentially, in other words, this is
like from the earlier פשט that you didn't like particularly. Right. It's
מעשר אדם. Maaser Adam.
Well, yes. Right. Right. No, he's correct. So therefore because of that
focus, not just on naturally which year it's from but because of
what you've done to process it and so on, therefore in that
case we actually do have to worry about the original amount. We
do focus on there was a component here that had a status
and the original stuff that grows doesn't negate and the new stuff
that grows does not negate the original. So just to take a
step back, I know this is very confusing, but basically what we
have said is the question is you have a core that continues
to grow, does the new stuff negate the original? We have evidence
that by שמיטה it does. We have evidence that by מעשר it
does not. The original is still there. And the גמרא answer basically
is that שמיטה is an exception. The general rule is that the
stuff that grows does not negate the original and that would be
even by things like תרומות and מעשרות Maasros and things that grow
from the land, okay, because even those types of things ultimately the
focus still requires a human component and so on. Only by שמיטה
which it's all about which year did it grow from, the land
of which year did it grow from, that's something where we'll say
if it continues to grow in the eighth year we'll focus on
it, we'll define it as an eighth-year fruit, not a seventh-year fruit.
But everything else we're going to say there's an original core that's
here that's not בטל, there's new stuff, and that you can never
get rid of like that original core and you always have to
deal with it. Okay. We will wrap this very long discussion up
tomorrow.
And this is the לשון Lashon of אלא מהא Ella Me-ha in
נדרים. Nedarim.